<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle of moche learni[n]g, sent by saint Huldericus, Bisshoppe of Augusta, called Augsburgh, vnto Nicolas Bysshoppe of Rome, the fyrst of that name: agaynst the vnmaried chastitie of pryestes</title>
            <author>Ulric, Saint, Bishop of Augsburg, 890-973.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1547</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14200</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121060</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856249</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856249</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21778</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14200)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21778)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 157:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle of moche learni[n]g, sent by saint Huldericus, Bisshoppe of Augusta, called Augsburgh, vnto Nicolas Bysshoppe of Rome, the fyrst of that name: agaynst the vnmaried chastitie of pryestes</title>
                  <author>Ulric, Saint, Bishop of Augsburg, 890-973.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[26] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1547?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>"Possibly printed by A. Scoloker or an unidentified predecessor of his."--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-b (-a8, b7,8, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Celibacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21778:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21778:1"/>
            <p>AN EPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STEL OF MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che learni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, ſent by ſaint Hul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericus, Biſſhoppe of Auguſta, called Augſburgh, vnto Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas Byſſhoppe of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, the fyrſt of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: agaynſt the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maried Chaſtitie of Pryeſtes.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21778:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21778:2"/>
            <head>VNTO NICOLAS hys lorde and father, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mooſt vygylaunt Prouiſor of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Church of Rome, Hulderi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus by name onelye a Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe, oweth Loue as his ſonne or chylde, and feare as hys ſeruaunt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Her as I haue chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced of late dayes to fynde your decrees, ſent ouer vnto me, made vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynencye of Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes or Preeſtes, to be farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alyenate from dyſcretion: a cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne feare truelye with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe dyd vexe me: feare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of that, where it is ſayd that the ſentence of a Paſtor is to be dredde ande feared, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:21778:3"/> it be Iuſt or vniuſt. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye I feared the weake a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d feble hearers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryptur, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which ſcant whear a Iuſt cauſe is, do obeye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Sentence of it, &amp; moch mor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vniuſt they treade vnder fote, leaſt thoſe ſhulde bli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues by a Precepte of theyr owne free wyll, through the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous and importable tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe or vſurpi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of theyr Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. And ſorrowe, trulye and pytye it was vnto me, whyles I doubted howe the membres ſhulde be ware of them ſelues, theyre heade beyng taken in ſo greuous a ſyckenes. For what can be more weightie, or what more worthy then the pitye or compaſſyon of the whole Chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che? Ande theryn you the Byſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhoppe of the hygheſt ſeate (vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to whome apparteyneth the ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amynatyon of the whole Chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che) to ſtraie neuer ſo litell ou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te
<pb facs="tcp:21778:3"/> of the waye, from the holye Diſcretion? Ande truelye you haue gone not a lytell out of the waye. when that you wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Clerckes or Prieſtes (whome you ought to moue to contynencye of wedlocke) to be compelled vnto the ſame by a certeyne Imperious violence. Why is not thys (thynke youe) iuſtly by the common Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all wyſe men a violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, when contrarye to the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Goſpell, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the decree of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Holy Gooſt, any Man is compelled to execute pryuate decrees? Where ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many holye exemples are of the Olde ande Newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (as you knowe) that teach Dyſcretion. Lett it not be (I praye youe) greuous vnto your Fatherhod, a fewe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, amongeſt many, to be graffed
<pb facs="tcp:21778:4"/> &amp; intermixed i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this litell boke. The Lorde of truth in the olde lawe hath appoynted vnto a Pryeſt wedlocke, the whych is not redde where afterward he hath forbydden the ſame: But he ſayth in the Goſpell. Math. xix. There are ſome gelded par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons that haue chaſtyſed them ſelues for the Kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: But all men vnderſtand not thys ſayinge, let him take it that maye take it. Wherfore the Apoſtell ſayth. i. Corin. vii. I haue no precept of the Lord for vyrgynes, but I giue them my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell. Wherby thou doeſt conſyder accordyng to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſaying of the Lorde, that all can not take thys counſell. But thou ſeeſt many flaterers of the ſaid cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell, that are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to pleaſe men a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not God, to commytt manny greuous thynges vnder theyr colour of
<pb facs="tcp:21778:4"/> contynencye, to vſe vnlaufullie the Fathers wyues, and not to abhorre from the embraſyng of the male kinde, and of Beaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Leaſt therfore the eſtate of the whole congregatyon maye chaunce to be to moch weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by the callyng aboute of thys infyrmytye, growynge e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto a very plage: Becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of fornycatyon (ſayde he) let euery man haue his owne wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe. The whych theſe ypocrytes faine to parteyne ſpecialie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to laye men. The whych albeyt that they be conſtytuted in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo holie an order, yet doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te they not in dede to abuſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mennes wyues. And (the which we ſee not without tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res) all men rage in the aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named miſcheues. Truelie tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe haue not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures a ryght, oute of whoſe pappes (becauſe they haue preſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:21778:5"/> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to harde) they haue dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken bloude in the ſteade of myl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke. For that ſaynige of the Apoſtell, let euery manne ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue hys owne wyfe, doth trulye except no man, ſauing the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour of contynencie (or hym that hath preſcribed in the lord to contynewe in hys vyrgyny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye. The whyche thyng (mooſt reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de Father) doth become your mighty power, that whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re any ſhalbe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal make vnto you by hand or by mouth, anye vowe of chaſtitie, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d afterwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des wyll forſake it, to bynde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame of duety to execute the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me vowe, or to depoſe the ſame oute of all orders by your Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nonycall auctoritye: ande that you maie be able, manly to ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyll the ſame, you ſhal haue me and all other men of my calli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to be vnto you dilyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ayders. But to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that you may
<pb facs="tcp:21778:5"/> knowe that ſoch as knowe of no ſoche vowe, are not to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled: heare the Apoſtell ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng vnto Tymothe: ſayinge, It becometh a Biſſhoppe to be irreprehenſible, the huſband of one wyfe. And becauſe that no man ſhulde returne the ſame ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence to the Church alone, he added vnto it. He truelye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can not gouuerne his owne houſe, howe ſhall the ſame giue dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce vnto the Church of God? Ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kewyſe he ſayth, let Deacons be huſbandes of one wyfe, the whych can well gouuerne their chylderen and houſes. And ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely I knowe, that you are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficyently taught, by the holy decrees, of the holie Biſſhoppe Sylueſter: that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyfe is bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Prieſt. Vnto theſe ande ſoch lyke ſentences of the Scrypture, the wryter of the rule of Prieſtes or Clerkes,
<pb facs="tcp:21778:6"/> accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, not whithout cauſe, ſaythe, a pryeſte oughte to be chaſte, or at the leaſt fettered wyth the bond of one Matry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monye. Of the whych thinges, he doth trulye gather, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d deacon, are noted to be worthy blame, yf they be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in manye women. Ande yf they refuſe one, vnder pretence of religion: Here the canonicall ſentence doth condempne both Byſſhop and deacon, wythout differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of degrees. A Biſſhop or Pryeſt ought not to caſt of his proper wife, vnder the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of relygyon: for yf he ſo doo, he ought to be excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nycate, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yf he continue to be depoſed. Saynt Auguſtine al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, a man not Ignoraunt of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye dyſcretyon, ſayth: There is none ſo greuous an euel but it is to be admytted to eſchewe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſe. We reade alſo in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde
<pb facs="tcp:21778:6"/> booke of Trypartita hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torya Canon dyſcuc. xvi. Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo Si quis. that when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Nyce, wolde haue eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſſhede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelue ſame decrees, that Byſſhoppes, Pryeſtes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d deacons, after theyr fyrſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecratyon ſhuld vtterlie abſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne from theyr proper wyues, or ſhuld put of theyr degree.</p>
            <p>Paphnutius riſing in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of them, (one of thoſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs which Maximus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour) (theyr ryght eies bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g plucked oute, and their lyft leg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges cutt of) did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne, ſpake agaynſt it: confeſſyng mariage to be honourable, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d affyrmi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g chaſtitie to be the lyuing with a mans proper wyfe. And per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded the counſell, that they ſhulde make no ſoche lawes, af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyrming y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe to be greuous, ande myght be vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theyr wyues an occaſyon of
<pb facs="tcp:21778:7"/> fornication. And this did Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phnutius expreſſe (albeyt he was vnmaryed) And the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell prayſed his opinion or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and decreed nothyng of that parte, but left that in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye mannes wyll, and of no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſytye. There are ſomme that take. S. Gregory to be an hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe vnto their ſecte. At whoſe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meritie I laughe, ande doo la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment theyr Ignoraunce, for why? They are Ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that the decree of this ſo perilous a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereſye, made by. S. Gregory was afterwarde with worthie frute of repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, purged by the ſame: for vppon a certeyne daye when he had caſt his net into hys po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de or ſtewe for fiſh, and ſawe aboue ſyx thouſande infauntes heades to be drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp, he (taken with inwarde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce) lamented, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyng the decree that was ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:21778:7"/> by hym ſelf, for abſteynynge from matrymonye to be a cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of ſo great a murther: pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the ſame (as I haue ſayde) wyth the frutes of worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce. And hys owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree vtterlye condempned, he ſayde that ſayinge of the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell. Better it is to Mary, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to burne. Addynge for his ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne parte, Better it is to Mary then to gyue an occaſyon of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath. Thys chaunce, peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re if they had redde wyth me (I thynke) they wolde not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue Iudged ſo raſhlye: at the leaſt fearynge the precept of GOD. Iudge ye not, that you be not Iudged a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of that Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſayth, What arte thou that thou doeſte Iudge an other mannes ſeruaunt? Vnto hys Lorde he ſtandeth or falleth: &amp; truly he ſhall ſtande, the Lorde is myghtie or able to ordeyne
<pb facs="tcp:21778:8"/> or dyſpoſe hym. Let therfore your holynes ceaſe to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne thoſe, whome you ought o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelie to admoniſh or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell: le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſt by a priuate precept (which God forbydde) you be founde contrarie as well vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> newe Teſtament, as vnto the olde. For as. S. Auguſtine ſaith vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Donatus, this onelye do we feare in your Iuſtice, Leaſt not for the conſideration of Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyan lenitie or gentelnes: But for the greatnes of the myſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe it ſelfe, you ſuppoſe it mete to be reſtrained: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which thing, for Chryſtes ſake, we deſyre you hertelye not to doo: for why? Sinnes are to be ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe maye remaine, that may be repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaying of. S. Auguſtyne, we wyll you alſo to remembre, where he ſayth: Let nothyng be done for the deſyre to do harme: and
<pb facs="tcp:21778:8"/> all thynges wyth Charytie to geue Conſell, lett nothinge be done cruellye, nothing vngent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. Alſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame I doo exhort you in the feare of Chryſte, all you that haue not Temporall thinges, couet not to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ande all youe that haue them, preſume not in them. I ſaye not, yf you haue them that you are conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned: but if you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume in them, you are conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Yf you ſeme vnto your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues for ſoche thinges to be me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of great aucthoritie. Yf for youre exellent vnytie, you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gett the commune condycion of mankinde. The which cuppe of diſcretion truelye, ye maye drawe oute of that Apoſtolyke fountayne. Arte thou vnloſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a wyfe, will not to ſeke for a wife. Arte thou bounde vnto a wife, will not to ſeke to be vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loſed. Where afterwarde it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.
<pb facs="tcp:21778:9"/> Thoſe that haue wyues ought to be as though they had none. Ande thoſe that vſe the woorld, as though they vſed it not. Alſo he ſpeaketh of the wyddowe: Let hyr ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Whome ſhe wyll, onelye in the LORDE. For truely to mary in the Lord, is to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt nothinge in the makyng of the Maryage, that the Lord doth forbydde. Hiremye alſo ſayth: Truſt youe not in Wordes of lyinge: Sayinge, the Temple of the LORDE, the Temple of the Lorde, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Temple of the LOGDE is, the which thing, Hierome expoundynge, ſayth: The ſame alſo maye agree vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe Virgynes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crake of theyr Virginytye, wyth an vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhamfaſte countenaunce, they ſett forth theyr Chaſtity, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr Conſcyence meaneth an other thyng. And they forgett
<pb facs="tcp:21778:9"/> the Diffinition of the Apoſtell of a Virgin: That ſhe ought to be Holy in Body and Spirite. What proffyteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chaſtnes of the Bodye, when the mynde is oppreſſed wyth whoredome? And if ſhe haue not other Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, that the Wordes of the Prophet doth deſcrybe? The whyche truelye becauſe we ſee you partly to haue, and becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe it is not vnknowen vnto vs, that your Dyſcretion (albeyt in this it be neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) in other Inſtitutions of youre lyfe, the ſame is preſerued. We diſpayr not, but that you will ſone cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rect y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euell faulte of this inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And therfor we do not taunte this youre neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (albeit it be very greuous) w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo great a grauity, as we may do. And (al though truly vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> termes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are vſed) a biſſhop ſhuld appere to be greter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>n a prieſt: yet ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe
<pb facs="tcp:21778:10"/> we not, Auguſtyne to be leſſe then Hierome. And a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reccion or a checke is not to be refuſed or diſdained of eueri i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feryoure, ſpecially wheare as he that is checked, is founde to trauayle agaynſte the trouth, ande to pleaſe men. Nor yet we ought to take the Dyſputa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions of euery Parſon (as S. Auguſtyne ſayth to Bonifaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us) although they be neuer ſo CATHOLYKE, ande well prayſed menne. As we do the Canonicall Scryptures: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, it be not laufull (ſauynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Honor that is due vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to dyſproue ande refuſe anye thynge in theyr wrytynge: If perchance we fynde that they Iudge othere wyſe then the trueth is: The whyche by the healpe of GOD, is eyther par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued by other, or by vs. And truelye what can be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye
<pb facs="tcp:21778:10"/> vnto the Verytye, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys? When the Verity itſelfe ſpeakynge of the contynenye, not of one man, but playnelye of all (except y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nombre of ſoche as are profeſſed to continency) ſayth: He that can take it, take yt, the whyche thynge theſe menne (wherof no Man kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth) beynge Prouoked or prycked to it, maye chaunce to ſaye, he that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take it, let hym be ſtryken wyth a curſe. What trulye can be done by me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more Foolyhe? What can be more bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnto the curſe of GOD? Than where as ſome, that is to ſaye: Eyther Byſſhoppes or DEACONS, are ronni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſo headlonge into the Luſtes of the Bodye: That they can neyther abhorre Adulterye, nor inceſte frome the mooſte Shamefulle Embracynge of the male kynde (the moore
<pb facs="tcp:21778:11"/> ſhame) and yet they ſaye, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Maryage of Pryeſtes ſtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnto them: and wyll not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre the Pryeſtes as fellow ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauntes to abſteyne from ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thynges, by the compaſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ryght Iuſtyce, or at the leaſte monyſh them to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynent: but commande them, as though they were ſeruaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ande compell them to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayne. Vnto the whych ſo foolyſh ande ſhamefull ſuggeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyons of ſoche Imperie (I will not ſaye counſell) they adde, it is more honeſtye to be intry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſecretlye wyth many wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, then openlye in the face of men and in conſcyence to be bound wyth one. Ande what trulye wolde they not ſaye? yf they were of hym ande in hym that ſayth, woo be vnto yowe Pharyſeys, the whych do all thynges for men. Ande by the
<pb facs="tcp:21778:11"/> Pſalmyſt, becauſe they pleaſe menne, they are confounded: for as moche as the Lord hath dyſpyſed them. Theſe be the men whych ſhuld fyrſt perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vs, that in hys ſyght (vnto whome all thynges are naked and open) we ought to be a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be ſynners, rather then in the ſyght of menne, to appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to be without ſpotte. Albeit therfore that ſoche through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſertes of theyr noughtynes, deſerue counſell of no pitie. we notwithſtandyng remembri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g our humanitie, do miniſter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell of Goddes Auctoritie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neuer wanteth pi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bowelles of Chary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For trulye this we ſaie: O y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ypocrit, caſt oute firſt a block oute of thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> owne eie, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſee, to caſt out a moate oute of thy brothers eie. And we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre them alſo to note, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinge
<pb facs="tcp:21778:12"/> that the Lorde ſayth of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone woman. Looke which of you is without ſynne, let hym caſt fyrſt the ſtone vppon hyr. As who wolde ſaye, yf the lawe doth commaunde it? Yf Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes do commaunde it? I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde it alſo. But I requyre mete or competent mynyſters of the lawe. Note well what you adde: ande marke well (I praye you) what you are: for if thou loke well vppon thy ſelfe (as ſcrypture ſayth) thou wylt neuer ſclaunder any man. It is alſo ſygnyfyed vnto vs, of certei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of thoſe, the which ſwell wyth ſo moche pryde in theyr owne conceyte, that they preſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me to pyll the flocke of the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, (for whome Gods ſhephear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des doubte not to mynyſter or gyue theyr ſoules) wyth ſtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes wythout reaſon. Whoſe ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. S. Gregory lamenting,
<pb facs="tcp:21778:12"/> ſaith: What ſhall become of the ſhepe, when the Shepheardes are made wolues? But who is ſoner ouercome, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth? Who ſhall Iudge the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecuter, but he that doth miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pacyentlie hys backe to the whippes? Trulie it weare well done, that it myght be hearde, for what frute the Churche of GOD ſhulde ſuffer ſo great a ſclaunder, &amp; the clergie ſo great a deſpyte of the Byſſhoppes, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of theyr infidelles. And verelie I doubte not, to call thoſe infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delles, of whome the Apoſtell Paul ſayth vnto Timothe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the latter dayes, ſome ſhall go awaye from the faith, geui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g care vnto the ſpyrytes of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and vnto the doctryne of Deuelles, ſpeaking lies in ypo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cryſye, hauyng a fyred conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, forbyddyng to marry. Thys trulye if it be throughly
<pb facs="tcp:21778:13"/> and dyligently ſeen, is the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of all theyr cockell, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the content of all theyr madnes, that whyles clerkes or Pryeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, (beyng ouercome wyth a Phariſaycall furour) are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to forſake the laufull co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye of one woman, fornyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, adulterers &amp; the ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full myniſters of other Praui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, are made lyke wyth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Theſe be they that doo bryng into the Church (lyke the blyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that leadeth the blynde) this hereſye, that the ſaying of the Pſalmyſt maye be fulfylled: Where lyke one for knowyng of theyr errour, he curſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after this ſorte. Let theyr eies be di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med or bleared that they ſee not, and theyr backe alwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes bowed downe. For as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che therfore as no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (O Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolyke Father) that knoweth you, is ſo Ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but yf you
<pb facs="tcp:21778:13"/> had foreſeen, by the clearenes of your ſubſtancyall dyſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo great a plage to be lyke to growe, through the ſentence of your decree: you would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue conſented vnto ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell ſuggeſtyons of any maner of parſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Wherfore by the fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delytye of pure due ſubiection, we counſell you: that nowe at the leaſt you laye watche, to putte awaie ſo great a ſclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the Church of God. And by your learnyng (as you knowe howe) to plucke vp by the rootes oute of the hearde of God: the doctryne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeys: Leaſt the onelye dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the lorde (yf ſhe vſe any longer vntrue huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des) pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke awaye the holie nation, the pryncelye pryeſthoade by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorſe, that can not be recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe, from hyr dere ſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe: that is to ſaye CHRIST.
<pb facs="tcp:21778:14"/> For as moch as no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without chaſtytye (not onelye in the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of vyrgynytye, but alſo in the knot of Matrymony) can ſee the Lorde, the whych ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and reygneth, wyth God the father, and the holyghooſt worlde wythout ende Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21778:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
